We all probably have a certain image of
Elizabeth as this glamorous, ageless
beauty.
And that was no accident.
Elizabeth's [music] reign is absolutely
synonymous with portraits.
>> There are over a hundred [music]
surviving images of Elizabeth that date
from her lifetime.
>> Anybody in a position of [music]
leadership and authority has to display
their image.
She knew she needed to be seen to be
believed. [music]
Portraits in Elizabeth's reign aren't
simply to be hung on walls and to
accurately represent the queen.
>> Elizabeth was the mistress of
propaganda.
>> It was the most audacious work of spin
centuries before [music] the kind of
political spin doctors that we think
about today.
The idea that a woman could rule for so
many decades unmarried [music] without
being deposed and being regarded now as
a monarch of great [music] success is
just incredible really. She's gone from
being Henry [music] VII's daughter, a
princess with very little chance of
succeeding to the throne to a queen of
England who's [music] trying to navigate
her way in a man's world. We see her in
her portraits go from a girl to an icon.
[music]
At the turn of the 16th [music] century,
portraiture in England was still very
much in its infancy. In fact, in terms
of the European perspective, [music] it
was way behind.
In the low countries, for example,
portraiture had started to become really
popular and the same in Italy. [music]
And we start to see lots of artists
coming from other European [music]
countries to seek patronage in places
like France where we get Leonardo da
Vinci. And then we get the German
[music] artist Hans Holine who arrives
at the court of Henry VIII in the 1530s.
And this is really a huge turning point
[music] for English portraiture because
Holine's focus is very much on realism
and attention [music] to detail. And
suddenly the portraits that have once
been very flat, very two-dimensional
[music]
become very real with the individual
leaping out from the canvas.
We also see at Henry VII's court that
[music] miniatures start to become more
popular as well because they are
portable. So they're more personal.
They can be used and [music]
incorporated into jewels for example. So
we know that Henry VI sixth wife
Katherine Par was very fond of [music]
miniatures.
Henry VII, Edward V 6th and Mary I all
had portraits of themselves [music]
painted and we see this happening across
Europe as well. monarchs, rulers,
members of the royal family all start to
have portraits of themselves [music]
being painted.
>> Increasingly during Henry's reign and
obviously with his children growing up,
but then through into Elizabeth's reign,
portraits and portrait miniatures in
particular became really important as
part of the diplomatic marriage networks
as well as being a sign of loyalty that
courtiers would have hung in their
houses or even, you know, really small
miniatures around their necks.
Elizabeth was the only child of Henry by
Amberlin.
She was born on the 7th of September
1533 at Greenwich Palace. And to begin
with, at the time of her birth, she was
the king's official heir. But this
wasn't a state of affairs that Henry was
prepared to accept. and Elizabeth was
born very much in the anticipation that
a brother, a male heir, would soon
follow. Tragically, this never
transpires. And before her third
birthday, Elizabeth's mother, Amberlin,
was executed on charges of adultery and
incest, charges that were almost
certainly falsified. And from that point
on, Elizabeth is declared illegitimate.
And it's a state of affairs that is
never rectified by her father because
although Elizabeth is later restored to
her place in the line of succession, her
father never legally legitimates her.
And this is a sticking point that
Elizabeth is forced to fight against for
the rest of her life. Um particularly
when she becomes [music] queen and she
uses portraiture as a way of asserting
her legitimacy.
>> [music]
>> There aren't actually many surviving
portraits of Elizabeth [music] that date
from before her time as queen, but the
family of Henry VIII is one of the
earliest that [music] we have, which
once hung in the palace of Whiteall,
where it's actually set.
It was commissioned [music] by Henry
VIII in around about 1545.
It's a dynastic piece as it's intended
to emphasize continuity within the TUDA
[music] dynasty.
The central focus is Henry sat in the
middle who is flanked [music]
by Jane Seymour, his third wife, who
crucially is dead at this point. But her
inclusion [music] is merited because she
had been the mother of the king's longed
for male heir, Prince Edward, [music]
who we can see on the king's other side.
In a way, it was [music] an attempt to
sort of try and forget all the chopping
and changing of Henry's marriages and
instead really suggests a happy family
situation that actually of course
infamously didn't exist.
Although Henry did not intend that
either of his daughters [music] should
succeed him, they were still an
important part of Henry's family and
that's why Mary and Elizabeth are
included.
Around her neck, Elizabeth wears an
initial jewel. And initial jewels were
extremely [music] popular in the 1530s
and 1540s. But one thing about this
piece [music] in particular is striking.
It represents the initial A, which can
[music] only be representative of
Elizabeth's mother, Amberlin. So why
would Elizabeth choose [music] to
identify herself with Amberlin in this
blatant piece of TUDA propaganda?
Perhaps it was a symbol of loyalty.
Perhaps this necklace had been given to
her. Unfortunately, it's [music] one of
the questions that we'll never be able
to know the answer for sure.
It was probably the following year when
another portrait of Elizabeth was
[music] painted, perhaps on her father's
orders. And throughout her life,
Elizabeth [music] was extremely fashion
conscious. And this portrait really
reflects that because she was dressed in
the finest [music]
and the costliest materials. She's got
crimson satin and [music] she's also
wearing a very magnificent collection of
jewels. But [music] the emphasis on this
portrait when Elizabeth was around 13
years old [music] is really her learning
and her piety because you can see she's
got her finger marking the page of a
[music] book. It's probably a copy of
the Bible or the New Testament.
This really emphasizes Elizabeth's
scholarly abilities for which she
[music] was renowned.
Having been this demoted figure after
[music] the execution of her mother
Amberlin, Henry's final wife, Katherine
Parr, has gone to great efforts to try
and bring the family back together. In
some ways, she was a very precocious,
very intelligent young woman, proficient
in languages. Katherine Parr was an
educated learned woman too who with
Elizabeth together they would read the
Bible they would conduct translations
[music]
so this represents a pious precociously
[music] intelligent and able young woman
at the end of her father's life about to
[music] face the prospect now of her
young brother Edward V 6 becoming king.
The [music] other thing to note about
this portrait is that Elizabeth is very
clearly [music] being identified as
Henry VII's daughter as per the
inscription [music]
which says Elizabeth the king's
daughter. So she's not legitimate
[music] but she is still an important
part of Henry VII's family. And this
portrait [music] also later appears in
Henry VII's inventory which suggests
that it may have been commissioned on
his orders.
In 1553,
Elizabeth's halfsister Mary succeeds as
Queen of England and she's the first
queen pregnant of [music] England to be
crowned. The idea of female monarchy is
quite unpopular because it's
unprecedented [music] in England. People
are unsure about what's going to happen
and Elizabeth has a particularly [music]
difficult time under Mary. In 1554, she
was accused of [music] complicity in the
Wyatt rebellion to overthrow her
halfsister.
Much to her distress, she was forced to
endure [music] a spell of imprisonment
in the Tower of London. And given that
her mother met her end [clears throat]
there, we can only imagine Elizabeth's
[music] terror at this perilous
situation.
On the anniversary of her mother's
execution, [music]
Elizabeth is released from the tower.
Um, but she's taken to endure a spell of
house imprisonment under the [music]
custodianship of Sir Henry Beddingfield.
And it's very clear that Mary harbors
this huge distrust [music] for
Elizabeth.
Nevertheless, by [music] 1558, it was
very clear that Mary wasn't going to
produce any children of her own. She'd
experienced [music] probably two phantom
pregnancies. And it's only at this point
that Elizabeth's ascendancy [music] to
the throne has gone from being a
possibility to a certainty.
Mary died on the [music] 17th of
November 1558 and Elizabeth succeeded to
the throne on a wave of popular and
heartfelt enthusiasm.
On the 15th of January [music] 1559,
Elizabeth was crowned at Westminster
Abbey.
We see [music] a dramatic change in
Elizabeth's portraiture as well from the
time that she becomes queen because
she's gone from being Henry VII's
daughter, a princess with very little
chance of succeeding to the throne
[music] to a queen of England who's
trying to navigate her way in a man's
world and [music] establish and certify
her authority. And portraiture provides
a very important way for her to do this.
It may have been around this time that a
portrait depicting her in full
coronation regalia was painted [music]
to mark the occasion. Although the only
surviving image we have of this now
dates from much later in Elizabeth's
life.
So it's depicting a 26-year-old queen
even [music] though it was painted in
1600 when Elizabeth was coming to the
end of her life. And here we have the
classic image of of queenship. [music]
Elizabeth holding the orb and scepter
wearing her man mantle showing herself
enthroned as she would appeared at the
coronation and this in a way is the kind
of poster girl image and I think many
people perhaps see this image as
representing the accession [music] of
the first queen such was the sort of
success and ubiquity of Elizabeth's
reign
but the reality here is in fact that
Elizabeth is wearing the handme-down
gowns of uh halfsister Mary who in fact
was the first crown queen of England
[music] and on Mary's death the the
coronation robe was hastily refurbished
but then worn again by Elizabeth and I
think that's a timely and instructive
reminder really that actually Elizabeth
did follow her sister Mary who did wear
the crown for the first time and in many
ways Elizabeth was able to learn from
her sister's mistakes but also kind of
benefit from the fact that it would been
Mary who had been the first woman to
wear the crown and had to negotiate
power and being a queen in what was
essentially still very much a man's
world.
The Hampton portrait which was
commissioned in the early 1560s
is a very rare fulllength portrait of
Elizabeth. is one of the only fulllength
images [music] that we have of the queen
and this was painted very early in her
reign when Elizabeth was the most
eligible bride in Europe.
So you can see the fruit and the foliage
in the background which is very much an
emphasis on fertility. The colors of red
and white that have been chosen in
Elizabeth's costume were an emphasis on
[music] the white rose of York and the
red rose of Lancaster that marked the
combined dynasties that Elizabeth had
descended from.
We can [music] also see Elizabeth
holding a glove in a sign of power. This
is very much an image that would [music]
have been sent out potentially to
suitors who were eager to obtain the
queen's hand in marriage.
It shows and represents the young queen
that she was at this point but actually
is [music] responding to a particularly
perilous time because quite soon after
Elizabeth's accession in 1562 [music]
she suffered from smallpox and indeed
for a time was unconscious there was a
sense that her life was very much in
danger and therefore the future was in
very precarious position and so this
really was a kind of attempt to
reestablish her authority after that
brush with death.
Thinking about her both as a tutor but
also as a future wife because although
she was queen at this [music] point, she
was also of course expected absolutely
to marry [music] not least to have a
male partner in government, women were
not regarded as able to govern and rule
on their own, but to provide an heir.
In the first few years of Elizabeth's
reign, [music] the emphasis was very
much on who was the queen going to
marry. And particularly in 1559, [music]
rumors began to abound of Elizabeth's
relationship with her [music] favorite,
Robert Dudley. Of course, Robert Dudley
was married, although when his wife died
in mysterious [music] circumstances,
there were continued rumors that he
might end up managing to convince
Elizabeth to marry him. Unfortunately
for him, [music] the death of his wife
put an end to all of those hopes because
Elizabeth realized that to marry him now
would permanently tarnish [music]
her reputation.
And again there was suggestion among
hostile agents and ambassadors that
actually perhaps uh she wasn't even a
virgin that she [music] in fact had
slept with Robert Dudley and others or
that she had some kind of physical
[music] impediment which meant that she
couldn't have children and therefore
wouldn't be a desirable marriage
prospect to a foreign prince. [music] So
these portraits are saying she's
fertile, she's chased, she's all the
things that you would want [music] as
well as trying to emphasize her
authority.
And we begin to see in this period the
need to mask the fact that actually
she's getting old.
It's important to remember that
Elizabeth [music] represented for the
Catholics of Europe and of course the
Catholics in [music] England. Those who
had been loyal to Katherine of Araggon
and then to Elizabeth's [music] sister
Mary. She was this illegitimate
pretended queen who should not have
exceeded [music] the throne. She was
Protestant. She was unmarried and in
fact the rightful queen was the Catholic
Mary, Queen of Scots who on Elizabeth's
succession [music]
claimed the English throne. So
Elizabeth's position was precarious in
the early years and that was expressed
in a number of plots and rebellions.
So we begin to see an attempt to in
portraiture respond to a number of
different threats. First of all,
emphasizing the Queen's virginity.
>> At the beginning of the 1570s, there
were those at court privately who had
begun to suspect that Elizabeth may not
marry. But that was certainly not the
image [music] that she was trying to
project, which we can see in both the
Phoenix and the Pelican portrait, both
of which [music] were created by
Nicholas Hillard. Hilliard was actually
a goldsmith [music]
by trade and he didn't end up painting
very many half-length [music] portraits.
In fact, the Phoenix and the Pelican
portrait are two of the few half-length
portraits [music] that he ever painted
because Hillard's skill was really with
miniatures. But like Holine [music]
before him, the emphasis in his
paintings was really on realism and
[music] detail. Relatively recent work
has shown that these portraits [music]
came from the same workshop and actually
some of the tree dating has shown that
they were made around the same time. So
[music] we can see the pelican and the
phoenix portrait as a pair and we can
see the face pattern inverted.
>> The phoenix was a symbol that was used
regularly [music] by Elizabeth and it
was also symbolic of chastity and
rebirth. She is wearing a costume of the
very highest value.
Elizabeth was really renowned for her
wardrobe. And [music] when she died, she
reputedly had nearly 2,000 dresses, but
all of these were composed of separate
elements, which we can [music] see here.
We can see the magnificent rough that
she wears around her neck. We [music]
can see the fabulous sleeves and a
magnificent bodice, all of which had
been embroidered. [music]
This was really high status work of the
highest quality.
The pelican portrait [music] tries to
convey a similar message. It's named
because of the pelican jewel that
Elizabeth can be seen [music] wearing.
And like the phoenix, this was a symbol
that Elizabeth adopted fairly regularly
throughout her reign. The emphasis on
this portrait is really in motherhood
because the pelican was believed to draw
blood from its [music] own breast with
which to feed its young. So it's
symbolic of Elizabeth as the mother of
her nation.
At a similar sort of time that the
phoenix and the pelican portraits have
been painted, we've [music] also got the
Darnley portrait of Elizabeth.
We know that Elizabeth sat for [music]
at least five artists throughout the
course of her life. But this image is
particularly important [music] because
it was the face from this portrait that
many of Elizabeth's later portraits were
based on. this face pattern that became
the the officially sanctioned [music]
one which it was ordered had to be used
in portraits of the queen and all
portraits had to be signed off by
[music] the queen's sergeant painter
essentially creating a kind of
censorship around the image of Elizabeth
and we think that for the later
portraits of her reign it was actually
her ladies her ladies in waiting who
would sit for the portraits because the
gowns that they wear accord with [music]
those that appear In the wardrobe
accounts, essentially there's a cut and
paste job [music] that the face pattern
is then added into the image denoting
Elizabeth when in fact [music] Elizabeth
hadn't sat for the portrait herself.
The image has now very [music] sadly
faded from its original and Elizabeth
appears almost quite cold. What's also
really important about this piece
[music] is that it's a huge reflection
of status. So, we can see Elizabeth's
crown in the background. [music] We can
also see the double string of pearls
that she wears around her neck. She's
carrying an ostrich feather fan, which
may have been gifted to her by one of
her courtes. And also, there hangs a
particularly important [music] jewel
from her waist, which is a ruby
surrounded by images of several Roman
gods. [music]
And this is really intended as a
reflection of Elizabeth's classical
learning. [music] So the classics were
extremely popular in the 16th century
and we know that Elizabeth was extremely
fond of reading about the classics.
[music] So this also may have been a
gift from one of her cultures intended
as a compliment towards the queen's
learning.
The 1580s see the execution of Mary,
Queen of Scots, who's been Elizabeth's
prisoner for the last 19 years, and
Elizabeth faces a huge backlash from
Catholic Europe.
>> More and more, the prospect looms of
finally Spanish decisive action against
Elizabeth.
In the summer of 1588, Philip II of
Spain launched 130 ships, his infamous
[music] Armada, to set sail against
England. Elizabeth gave a rousing speech
to her troops at Tilbury in which she
urged them to [music] fight and made
that very famous saying, "I know I have
the body but of a weak and feeble woman,
but I have [music] the heart and stomach
of a king and a king of England, too."
In fact, this is a hugely defining
moment in Elizabeth's reign because the
Armada was the greatest threat [music]
that she had faced to date.
>> In many ways, [music] Elizabeth's reign
is absolutely identified with the defeat
of the Spanish Armada, [music]
although arguably it was more a victory
for the English weather.
But I would argue that actually the
Armada portrait [music] is incredibly
significant and powerful for its
symbolism.
And in a way it shows just how
successfully [music]
Elizabeth had over the course of her
reign managed to essentially override
the [music] reality of her femininity
and the idea that she was a woman with a
body that [music] was seen as weak and
problematic.
In fact, what she's doing in this
portrait [music] is using her body to
make as powerful a political statement
as Henry VIII did in [music] that famous
Holine mural.
What she's doing in this [music]
portrait is saying her body, her natural
body is one and the same as England.
What's really interesting in Elizabeth's
portraits at this time is they're full
of symbolism [music] and full of
messages.
And this one is very much of victory.
[music]
So, we see Elizabeth with her hand on
the globe. It's actually pointing at
Virginia, which had been named in her
honor as [music] the Virgin Queen. And
we see again the crown in the
background, symbolic of Elizabeth's
authority and of monarchy.
To her left, we see [music] the Spanish
ships which are being tossed around in
the sea, [music] are in utter turmoil
compared with the English ships on the
other side which are sailing [music] in
calm waters. And the message here is
Elizabeth's reign as being one of peace
and prosperity
by contrast [music] to the tunnel that's
taking place in Catholic Europe, which
Elizabeth is turning [music] her back
to.
Beside Elizabeth, we've got the figure
of a mermaid. And mermaids were [music]
believed to be temptation for soldiers.
It's this symbol of England triumphing
over Catholic Europe [music] whilst the
mermaid had been sent to tempt the
Spanish soldiers.
However, a lot of the imagery [music] in
this portrait is all a bit of an
illusion. It's sending out the message
that Elizabeth is all powerful, but it's
a [music] message that her government
and the queen herself wanted people
[music] to believe.
At a similar time to the Armada
portrait, we also have the rainbow
portrait of Elizabeth, which hangs in
Hatfield House.
>> I think this is one of my favorite
pictures of Elizabeth. It's kind of
audacious and [music] it's cunning.
She's still wearing the mask of youth
that we associate with her younger
portraits. This is very much a high
status portrait that is [music] intended
to dazzle, that's intended to impress
and to convey [music] Elizabeth's
magnificence.
She is wearing a rainbow. The Latin
inscription in the background basically
says that there can be no rainbow
without the sun. Elizabeth is the son.
She is the queen. She oversees
everything.
We can see that her dress shows a
[music] design of eyes and ears
reflecting the fact that Elizabeth was
believed to be able to see and hear
everything that was going on in her
kingdom which of course she was because
she had this tremendous spy network
[music] under the opaces of Francis
Walsingham at this time.
She also wears a serpent jewel on her
sleeve. This is a reflection of her
wisdom because [music] the serpent was
believed to be an extremely cunning
creature. She also wears the crown in
her headdress. Another indication of her
majesty.
So in a response to the reality which is
Elizabeth weak towards the end of her
reign feeling vulnerable in a
factionridden court but here instead
denoting [music]
power all knowing allseeing and a
youthful image of authority.
As we go into the 1590s, we're also
entering the last decade of Elizabeth's
reign. And it's a period when arts and
literature really begin to flourish.
[music]
And we can see this in the production of
a magnificent miniature, Elizabeth I and
the three goddesses. It represents
[music]
a classical story, the judgment of
Paris. when Paris awarded a golden apple
to Venus, the goddess of beauty, thereby
sparking the outbreak of the Trojan
[music] War.
However, in this image, Elizabeth is
seen holding the golden orb in a
reflection of the fact that she
encompasses all of the qualities of
[music] these three goddesses. So,
beauty, wisdom, and peace. So crucially,
this is a reflection that Elizabeth is
bringing peace rather than war to her
realm.
>> I mean, this is a kind of incredible
portrait, and it [music] shows just
quite how far portraits have evolved
over Elizabeth's reign, but also how
much of a job they're doing in terms of
spinning a line really. Here we've got
Elizabeth being celebrated for her
mythical divine powers, making her seem
[music]
this kind of divine celestial body that
somehow is now more than simply a queen
and indeed a a goddess figure.
In 1592, we also [music] see the
production of one of the most iconic
images of Elizabeth, the [music]
so-called Ditchley portrait.
This was probably commissioned by Sir
Henry Lee who was the Queen's champion
for many years and probably painted in
order to commemorate a visit [music]
that Elizabeth made to Sir Henry Lee at
his home at Ditchley near Oxford [music]
in 1592.
Sir Henry Lee had been living quite
openly [music]
with his mistress Anne Vavasur and she
had previously had an affair with the
Earl of Oxford which had earned both a
spell of imprisonment [music] in the
tower. However, the ditchly portrait
with its theme of forgiveness is
reflective of the fact that Elizabeth
has now accepted [music] that Sir Henry
Lee has been living openly with Anne.
Elizabeth is seen standing on the globe.
Again, she's wearing an extremely high
status, lavish costume, and some of the
jewels that she wears are possibly those
that can be identified in her 1587
inventory. So, these may have been
[music] real pieces that were owned by
Elizabeth.
It's also [music] depicting both the
shadows of the threats and the turbulent
years that had preceded this moment as
well as the prospect of light that
Elizabeth always brought. a sort of
goddess, celestial figure, but also just
far, of course, at odds with the reality
of [music] Elizabeth at this point when
she's in her 60s.
In the last few years of Elizabeth's
reign, life was quite difficult for many
[music] of her subjects because there
had been bad harvests and the economy
wasn't going particularly well. So the
standard of living had dropped.
It was now becoming clear that [music]
the queen was getting old. Her hair had
fallen out and she was reduced to
wearing wigs. [music] Her teeth had
rotted from eating the sugary
confections of which she was so fond.
[music]
But nevertheless, she did her best to
try and retain this mask of youth for as
long as possible. [music]
This is a newly authenticated portrait
which was thought to come from the
workshop of Marcus G, the painter of the
ditchly portraits. And this, it seems,
was a portrait that slipped through the
censorship net which attempted [music]
to catch any portraits which showed
Elizabeth aging which really depicted
her mortality. And you've got her crown
there sort of slipped off. It's really
[music] a sense of time marching on.
It gives us a kind of remarkable
tantalizing glimpse of of the reality
which for all of us [music] over
centuries it's kind of eluded us.
And I suppose some people draw parallels
[music]
with the very authentic picture of the
current Queen Elizabeth II [music] by
Lucien Freud.
In a way, [music] those two portraits
are interesting because for Elizabeth II
to be shown to be aging in the way that
the Lucian Freud uh [music] portrait
shows is is just a mark of her strength,
her longevity.
It shows in contrast here that actually
such lengths had been gone to to try and
[music] prevent this kind of image
emerging which showed that the end of
Elizabeth's reign she was really really
old and that of course would have been a
source of great deal of anxiety [music]
and uncertainty for people.
This really does show quite how duped
people have [music] been over the
centuries when we think of Elizabeth in
those mask of youth portraits when in
fact by the end this is more [music]
accurately what she would have looked
like.
On the [music] 24th of March603,
Elizabeth died at Richmond Palace. And
to begin with, there is a great sense of
mourning. However, there's also the
great hope and expectation of what the
reign of James I [music]
may bring.
We begin to see starting in around6007
this wave of nostalgia for the reign of
good Queen Beth, Queen Elizabeth. And
suddenly there's this huge mass of
revival in her portraits. And we see
this in an image that was probably
painted around 7 years after her death.
Finally, in many ways, you know, the
censorship and the control had been
lifted and people could reflect back on
Elizabeth as she would have been and
appeared at the end of her reign. And
so, this is really one of the more real
depictions of Elizabeth. Here is a queen
that looks careworn and looks exhausted.
We can see that in her pose with her
head rested on her hand. So no longer is
she the queen be decked in the
magnificent costumes and the magnificent
jewels trying to project an image of
majesty.
Over one shoulder we see father time
leaning and the other we see death.
The message is that even for a queen and
a queen as great as Elizabeth,
immortality isn't [music] an option.
Death comes to us all.
The portraits of Elizabeth's reign and
there were very many of them were
deliberately
creating and sustaining actually a
fiction and the fiction was first of all
that this is a young fertile prospective
bride when she first became queen, but
later that actually she is this selfless
virgin figure that she's this kind of
goddess figure that she is this
completely all knowing powerful [music]
figure whose influence stretches across
the country and potentially across the
globe. And all of this was to in [music]
some sense distract from the reality
which was Elizabeth was an unmarried
queen. So an unmarried queen was
problematic in terms of protecting her
reputation, but it was also of course
essential to marry to provide an heir
and preserve the succession. She needed
to [music] appear young because she
represented a dead end. The Tuna dynasty
died with her. And it's kind of
remarkable that Elizabeth is regarded
[music] I think as one of the great
monarchs of history because the reality
is she was this really negligent queen
who didn't do the job that every monarch
was [music] expected to do which was to
ensure the succession. She willfully
chose not to marry. She didn't even name
[music] an heir and then she died
essentially you know this woman who just
wanted to maintain the fiction [music]
that she was going to live forever. It
was the most audacious work of spin, you
know, centuries [music] before the kind
of political spin doctors that we think
about today.
Portraits are some of [music] the most
important sources that we have when
studying not only Elizabeth the Queen,
but also Elizabeth the woman.
Her image was very tightly controlled.
But what we also have to remember is
that there wasn't a great precedent for
female rule at this time.
Elizabeth's successors, the [music]
early Stewart kings, didn't have the
same kind of issues about gender or
about legitimacy [music] that Elizabeth
faced. So, their portraits were trying
to convey very different kinds of
messages.
Although Elizabeth herself believed in
the superiority [music]
of men, she believed that she herself
was the exception. And each of her
portraits provide a way of her conveying
this important message.
She's gone from a girl to a woman, from
a woman to a queen, and a queen who used
her image to [music] convey all kinds of
mysterious elements about her
personality and her queenship.
As someone whose path to the throne was
littered with uncertainty,
her image reflects her battle to
establish herself as one of the leading
female authorities [music] in Europe,
one of the most powerful women in
history.
[music]